So today's דף daf is ד. dalet. We pick up in the
middle of ג עמוד ב. Gimmel Amud Bet. We're still in the
middle of some of these discussions about things that a hierarchy of
which activities are of greater weight. The עבודה Avodah in the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah of the individual, תלמוד תורה
Talmud Torah of the רבים, rabbim, and מקרא מגילה. Mikra Megilla. And
again fitting into this larger theme about this tremendous weight that's given
to the מגילה, Megilla, so until now we've been dealing with it
as a text, almost as a biblical text in terms of דרשנ'ינג
darshaning פסוקים, psukim, sort of completely gliding over the fact that, glossing
over the fact that there's some sense of innovation in it. There
would be an innovation in a change of the look of the
letters, but the idea that there's a new holiday and that there's
this מצוה mitzvah of מקרא מגילה Mikra Megilla is seen, you know,
in juxtaposition. It's seen as absolutely no innovation, and here we're dealing
with the weight of the מצוה mitzvah of reading the מגילה, Megilla,
that it takes precedence over תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah and over the
עבודה. Avodah. So now the גמרא Gemara continues with that and says
the following: אמר רבא פשיטא לי עבודה ומקרא מגילה מקרא מגילה עדיף.
Amar Rava pshita li avodah umikra megilla mikra megilla adif. If it's
between the עבודה Avodah in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and reading
the מגילה, Megilla, reading the מגילה Megilla takes precedence. מדרב יוסף בר
חנינא, Midei Rav Yosef bar Hanina, like Rav Yosef bar Hanina like
we taught yesterday, that was where, that was where the discussion started,
right? And he learned it from the משפחה משפחה, mishpacha mishpacha, even
the משפחות כהונה ולויה. mishpachot kehuna uleviya. So it shows you the
tremendous weight. And also going back to the point that David made
yesterday, also the fact that even though this is a, I think
an excellent point that this is a גלות galus sort of holiday,
but and you're back in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael with the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, you know, and maybe you think the whole thing
is trivial at this point. Nevertheless, you even are מבטל mevatel the
עבודה, Avodah, the central sort of religious, you know, activity for the
sake of מקרא מגילה. Mikra Megilla. So that we established yesterday. תלמוד
תורה ומקרא מגילה מקרא מגילה עדיף. Talmud Torah umikra megilla mikra megilla
adif. And if it's between תורה Torah and מקרא מגילה, mikra megilla,
and תורה Torah is of course what takes the place of קרבנות,
korbanot, and learning מגילה, Megilla, then again מגילה Megilla comes first, מדסמכו
של בית רבי, mideismchu shel Beit Rabbi, from the, from the fact
that בית רבי Beit Rabbi established this principle that you're מבטלין תלמוד
תורה, mevatlin Talmud Torah, and even though the גמרא Gemara yesterday sort
of said the קל וחומר kal vachomer can only be made in
terms of תלמוד תורה דיחיד, Talmud Torah d'yachid, in the end the
גמרא Gemara is not really distinguishing, and you know, it's a little
ambiguous. Maybe you even מבטל mevatel תלמוד תורה דרבים Talmud Torah d'rabbim
for מקרא מגילה. Mikra Megilla. So everything, so מקרא מגילה Mikra Megilla
takes precedence over everything. Now here's my question, though: תלמוד תורה ומת
מצוה, Talmud Torah umet mitzvah, I'm sorry, no, not yet my question.
Here's another thing that's clear to me: תלמוד תורה ומת מצוה מת
מצוה עדיף. Talmud Torah umes mitzvah mes mitzvah adif. Now, so all
of these things,
so מגילה Megilla is greater than תורה Torah and it's greater than
עבודה, Avodah, you know another thing that's greater than תורה? Torah? מת
מצוה. Mes Mitzvah. If you have to involve yourself with the burying
of a dead body that nobody else is involved to bury. מדתיניא,
mideitanya, we turned in a ברייתא: Beraita: מבטלין תלמוד תורה להוצאת המת
ולהכנסת כלה. mevatlin Talmud Torah lehotza’as hamais ulehachnasas kallah. You negate תלמוד
תורה, Talmud Torah, meaning you, you know, leave the בית מדרש Beit
Medrash in order to accompany out a dead body to be buried
and for bringing in a bride, you know, for things that are
done that the larger the participation, you know, the greater the honor
that is given, whether it's a case of mourning, whether it's a
case of rejoicing, you know, these, then you're מבטל mevatel תלמוד תורה
Talmud Torah for this sake. Now תוספות Tosafot points out, because you
know, הכנסת כלה hachnasat kallah is not the same as מת מצוה,
mes mitzvah, and this doesn't say you do it for the sake
of מת מצוה. mes mitzvah. So if you take a look at
תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says מת מצוה עדיף. mes mitzvah adif. Little
תוספות Tosafot here, לאו דוקא מת מצוה. lav davka mes mitzvah. The
first מת, mes, תוספות, Tosafot, מת: mes: לאו דוקא מת מצוה אלא
הדין לכל מתים שבעולם מבטלין תלמוד תורה להוציאם. lav davka mes mitzvah
ela hadin lechol maisim sheba'olam mevatlin Talmud Torah lehotzi'am. Oh,
but because in a minute we're going to be talking about מת
מצוה, mes mitzvah, we say מת מצוה mes mitzvah here. But the
reality is, now of course that doesn't mean that every time there's
a funeral everybody leaves the ישיבה. yeshiva. There are, you know, there
are standards. Is it לפי כבודו lefi kevodo or not לפי כבודו,
lefi kevodo, you know, of the מת? mes? But if there's a
sense that for the burial more people are needed for it to
be done in an appropriate way, then that would take and there
other, aren't other people to do that, then that would take precedence
even over תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah. Okay, so you don't even have
to get to this stage of מת מצוה. mes mitzvah. Certain types
of הוצאת המת hotza'at hamet you're מבטל mevatel תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah
for them. Okay. עבודה ומת מצוה, Avodah umes mitzvah, similarly if it's
between the עבודה Avodah in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and מת
מצוה, mes mitzvah, and here we do mean מת מצוה mes mitzvah
specifically,
then מת מצוה עדיף. mes mitzvah adif. Again, מת מצוה mes mitzvah
takes precedence. If there's nobody else to bury, then כהן kohen would
leave the עבודה Avodah in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash to take
care of it. How do you know? From the verse that says
ולאחותו, velachoto, that it says and to his sister. This is about
the נזיר. Nazir. It also by a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol that
you're not מיטמא mitameh even to immediate family relatives. A normal כהן
kohen is, but a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is not, and a
נזיר Nazir is not. And from the fact that the תורה Torah
tells all the relatives you're not מיטמא mitameh for, even though it
already said he's not מיטמא mitameh for any relative, we learn an
extra thing out of each word. ותניא, u'tanya, we taught in a
ברייתא Beraita the
following: ולאחותו מה תלמוד לומר, velachoto mah talmud lomar, why is it
telling you ולאחותו? velachoto? And רש"י Rashi tells you the background, that
the background is it says על כל נפשות מת לא יבא, al
kol nafshot mes lo yavo, right, by a נזיר Nazir he cannot
come. contact with any dead, לאביו ולאמו לאחיו ולאחותו לא יטמא להם
במותם כי נזר אלהיו על ראשו le'aviv ule'imo le'achiv ule'achoto lo yitama
lahem bemotam ki nezer elokav al rosho or something like that. So
into anybody he can't come in contact to anybody and then it
spells out father, mother, brother, sister. So why does it have to
spell it out? It already said not everybody. So basically says no
matter what else is... I'm sorry, excuse me, I skipped that. So
it says because the חידוש chiddush is, yes, normally you don't, you're
not מטמא metame to anybody, even an immediate relative. But then the
fact that it starts spelling it out like לאביו le'aviv etc. means
okay, you're not מטמא, metame, why does it have to say לאביו
le'aviv if it already said you're not מטמא metame to a relative?
To tell you that even though you're not מטמא metame to a
relative, but you would be מטמא metame to a מת מצוה. mes
mitzvah. So in a certain ironic classic rabbinic way, since the תורה
Torah already said you're not מטמא metame to anyone and then it
repeats it again and not even a father, not even a mother,
each repetition is saying these people you're not מטמא metame to because
all they are are relatives. But if there's a מת mes around
and presumably let's say there's another relative available to bury, but if
there's a מת mes around that there is nobody to bury, for
that type of a person you would be מטמא metame to. And
each one of those words makes it even more extreme. So let's
take a look how it's more extreme. So לאחותו le'achoto which is
the last of those words, right, לאביו ולאמו לאחיו ולאחותו le'aviv ule'imo
le'achiv ule'achoto gives you the most extreme case
that you would override for the sake of מת מצוה. mes mitzvah.
Because all of those are saying for the relative you're not but
for מת מצוה mes mitzvah you are. And even as more and
more and more extreme, you'll still be מטמא metame for מת מצוה.
mes mitzvah. So what is the example, what does לאחותו le'achoto teach
you? דתניא detanya we taught in a ברייתא. braitah. ולאחותו מה תלמוד
לומר? vele'achoto mah talmud lomar? Why does it say not to your
sister? To tell you not to your sister but yes to מת
מצוה. mes mitzvah. הרי harei and here's the example, an extreme example,
שהיה הולך לשחוט פסחו ולמול את בנו, shehaya holech lishchot picho velimol
et beno, somebody's going to שחט shacht a קרבן פסח korban pesach
and to give a ברית מילה bris milah to his son, two
big מצוות mitzvos that have to be done right now, certainly מילה
milah you could do שלא בזמנו shelo bizmano but you wouldn't get
the מצוה mitzvah of בזמנו, bizmano, פסח pesach if you don't do
it you're not doing it at all.
And ושמע שמת לו מת veshama shemet lo met and this person
heard that an immediate relative died. יכול יטמא? yachol yitama? Maybe he
should go ahead and involve himself in their burial. No, אמרת לא
יטמא. amarta lo yitama. It says that this נזיר nazir cannot come
in contact with any dead body. But יכול כשם שאינו מטמא לאחותו
כך אינו מטמא למת מצוה? yachol keshem she'eino metame le'achoto kach eino
metame lemes mitzvah? But maybe the same thing would be true not
just if it's a relative but even if it's a
מת מצוה. mes mitzvah. תלמוד לומר talmud lomar ולאחותו. vele'achoto. No, it's
only to your sister that this נזיר nazir is not מטמא. metame.
לאחותו הוא דאינו מטמא אבל מטמא למת מצוה. le'achoto hu de'eino metame
aval metame lemes mitzvah. He is מטמא metame to a מת מצוה
mes mitzvah and he's מטמא metame to מת מצוה mes mitzvah even
if what he has to give up is the fact that he's
not going to be able to bring the קרבן פסח, korban pesach,
he's not going to be able to do a ברית מילה bris
milah to his son. And what preceded this was also that the
person we might be talking about
could be a נזיר nazir who's a כהן גדול. kohen gadol. So
he has all of these other statuses that he would have to
override for the sake of מת מצוה mes mitzvah and negate all
these other מצוות mitzvos and nevertheless מת מצוה mes mitzvah overrides. So
this is very powerful and some extreme statements that the גמרא Gemara
makes
about what has to take precedence if there's a dead body and
it's not being given the treatment in the respect that or just
taken care of the way it needs to, how much that that
overrides in terms of the קדושה kedusha that it overrides, in terms
of the other מצוות mitzvos that it overrides. So back to our
point the גמרא Gemara is saying it's clear to me therefore that
מת מצוה mes mitzvah trumps עבודה avoda because this person is not
bringing the קרבן פסח korban pesach
and he's also a כהן גדול. kohen gadol. Anyway, so, no one
minute. So בעי רבא, baei Rava, so that all that is clear
to me. So what do I know?
I know that מגילה Megilla is greater than עבודה avoda and I
know that מגילה Megilla is
greater than עבודה avoda and it's greater than תלמוד תורה talmud Torah
and I know that מת מצוה mes mitzvah is greater than עבודה
avoda and greater than תלמוד תורה, talmud Torah, right? So what's the
one thing I don't know?
מת מצוה mes mitzvah or מגילה. Megilla.
Right, the relationship between מת מצוה mes mitzvah and מגילה. Megilla. So
בעי רבא, baei Rava, רבא Rava asked, מקרא מגילה ומת מצוה הי
מינייהו עדיף? mikra megilla umes mitzvah hai minaihu adif? But let's say
it's between מקרא מגילה mikra megilla and מת מצוה, mes mitzvah, which
one is more important?
Now given all the tremendous weight we give to מת מצוה, mes
mitzvah, it would be hard to understand how you could give more
importance to מגילה. Megilla. But now we're going to finally articulate where
some of the weight of מגילה Megilla comes from.
So מקרא מגילה עדיף משום פרסומי ניסא. mikra megilla adif mishum pirsumei
nisa. It's publicizing the miracle. And this is an important point about
what we're going to sort of be seeing about the idea of
it's not just an idea like certain things are דברים שבקדושה devarim
shebikdusha and you need a מנין. minyan. Here the idea is you
want everybody sort of actively participating in it because of the idea
of to publicize the miracle. And that might therefore since it's being
introduced here, but that might explain some of what we saw yesterday,
leave the בית המדרש, beis medrash, leave the... המקדש Hamikdash don't say
you'll read the מגילה Megillah on your own at a later time.
It's important that everybody comes together even if it means overriding עבודה,
avodah, overriding תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah. So the idea of פרסומי ניסא
Pirsumei Nisa is not just the doing of the מצווה, mitzvah, but
the bringing everybody together and that could explain some of the overrides
before. So maybe therefore it also overrides the מת מצווה. meis mitzvah.
או דילמא O dilma מת מצווה עדיף meis mitzvah adif. משום כבוד
הבריות, mishum kevod habriyos, right? And here the גמרא Gemara articulates the
theme of מת מצווה, meis mitzvah the honor due to God's creatures,
to human beings even in their death, and that fundamental thing of
letting a body just sort of you know there you know that
nobody's caring for and it's בזיון bizayon and it's you know
in disrespect and in disregard you know that would be a tremendous
that would be a huge problem. So which one takes precedence?
סופו דבעי אהדר פשטיה, Sofo debayei ahadar pashiteih, after he asked he
finally came to the conclusion, מת מצווה meis mitzvah, עדיף. adif דאמר
מר, De'amar mar, גדול כבוד הבריות שדוחה לא תעשה שבתורה. gadol kevod
habriyos shedocheh lo sa'aseh shebaTorah. The principle of כבוד הבריות kevod habriyos
is greater. How do I know the principle of כבוד הבריות kevod
habriyos is greater? Because it even overrides a negative prohibition in the
תורה. Torah. Until now we've been talking about which has precedence for
certain positive מצוות, mitzvos, but not overriding negative. Now this is based
on a גמרא Gemara in ברכות Berachos and the idea of overriding
a negative is you know is qualified there. It starts by the
idea that the גמרא Gemara learns that you don't somebody who would
not be
you know according to their honor to bend down and pick up
a lost object and return it, they wouldn't even do it for
their own object, they're like a sage or very elderly person it
would be considered beneath their dignity. So that person doesn't do it.
So he's not only is he מבטל mevatel the מצווה mitzvah of
השבת אבידה hashevas aveida but he's מבטל mevatel the negative מצווה mitzvah
of לא תוכל להתעלם, lo suchal lehitalem, ignoring the אבידה. aveida. But
the גמרא Gemara obviously limits that and mostly says that it overrides
דרבנן. de-Rabbanan. It's a very limited example of where it would override
דאורייתא. de-Oraisa. But nevertheless what is very significant is you know that
I think the counter-way in which unfortunately most people think which is
that religious activities are the more like ritual ones and the ones
that have to do with God, whereas the ones that have to
do with human beings, yeah that's just like ethics or morality, you
know obviously like religious activities take precedence. So you can be like
mean to someone or cheat them if you're going to use the
money for כבוד שבת kevod Shabbos or something like that. So here
you know the גמרא Gemara is in the end all of these
various activities give way to a מצווה mitzvah which is fundamentally based
on an issue of כבוד הבריות kevod habriyos and even a somebody
who is dead, the idea of כבוד הבריות kevod habriyos really trumps
all of these. Yes, Michael.
So didn't we just say a moment ago about תלמוד תורה Talmud
Torah versus מת meis and הכנסת כלה? hachnasas kallah? Yeah, right. And
what about the thing on שבת? Shabbos? אלו דברים שאדם אוכל
פירותיהם, Eilu devarim she'adam ochel peiroseihem, תלמוד תורה כנגד כולם. Talmud Torah
keneged kulam. And in that list was לוויית המת levayas hameis and
הכנסת כלה. hachnasas kallah.
Yes, so that's talking about the שכר sechar of the מצווה, mitzvah,
not about this momentary decision about what you have to do. Right.
So it's even
though the שכר sechar is greater for תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah nevertheless
in this instance you...
Exactly. For this moment, it's not like you're never going to learn
תורה Torah again in your life. For this moment you have to
address the immediate issue of... Yeah, the bigger חידוש chiddush is the
עבודה avodah because does it really mean the עבודה avodah won't get
done or does it mean it's being delayed? Like תלמוד תורה Talmud
Torah in the end is something that you're not doing now but
it's not like you lose an opportunity to do later, which is
important in general of questions about what is דוחה, docheh, you know,
עוסק במצווה פטור מן המצווה oseik bemitzvah patur min hamitzvah and all,
often תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah gives because it could be done later.
So alright.
And there's other reasons also why תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah might give
way to other מצוות. mitzvos. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this. But that's a good point that normally we say תלמוד תורה
כנגד כולם Talmud Torah keneged kulam but the weight of it doesn't
necessarily determine this issue of which takes precedence. Okay, so גמרא Gemara
says like this: גופא. Gufa. Alright, so that was the end of
that earlier discussion of like various hierarchies and we've introduced the principle
of פרסומי ניסא Pirsumei Nisa which again would it sort of make
the demand here the specific demand I don't care what you're doing,
everybody gets together to read the מגילה. Megillah. We'll see פרסומי ניסא
Pirsumei Nisa come up in other forms as well as we continue
today. גופא. Gufa. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי. Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi. Now back to specific issues about מקרא מגילה. Mikra Megillah. Says
רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, כרך וכל הסמוך לו
וכל הנראה עמו נידון ככרך. kerach vechol hasamuch lo vechol hanireh imo
nidon kekerach. So the כרך, kerach, the you know the walled city
and any place near it and visible to it has the same
status as the walled city and reads on the fifteenth. תנא, Tana,
we find in a ברייתא: Braisa: סמוך אף על פי שאינו נראה,
נראה אף על פי שאינו סמוך. samuch af al pi she'eino nireh,
nireh af al pi she'eino samuch. It's one or the other. If
you're close even if you're not visible, or if you're visible even
if you're not close. בשלמא נראה אף על פי שאינו סמוך, Bishlama
nireh af al pi she'eino samuch, so the גמרא Gemara says I
can understand an example of being visible without being too close. משכחת
לה כגון דיתבא בראש ההר. Mashkachas lah kegon deyavsa berosh hahar. So
if it's the city's at the top of the mountain so you
could have a village that's very far away but you got a
very good you know line of
sight. A good line of sight and you could see villages that
are far away. So that would also be considered to be part
of the כרך. kerach. That'd be fascinating like how far would that
go, you know, how many miles would that go? Okay. אלא סמוך
אף על פי שאינו נראה היכי משכחת לה? Ella samuch af al
pi she'eino nireh heichi mashkachas lah? How do you have something that's
nearby and remember yesterday we said nearby was within a מיל, mil,
within a kilometer? So how do you have something that's within a
kilometer that's not... not sort of visible? So what? Tall trees in
your way? Well, right. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רבי ירמיה
שיושבת בנחל, Amar Rebbi Yirmeya sheyeshevet benachal, it's the reverse of in
the city. The village is, the city is in a wadi and
the village is let's say on the level ground. So you can't
see from the city up to what's on the level ground even
though it is not so distant. Okay. Yeah.
נראה עמו nira imo doesn't mean to me that one is visible
from the other. It means that they're both visible from a certain
point from another point.
But what is that other point though?
Well, but let's say you have a mountain in between, right? So
I can't see from here to here, but from here I can
see both and they're both visible.
Yeah, but then how do you understand the answer of יושבת בהר?
yeshevet behar? I understand, you're right. נראה עמו nira imo means like
from a third
perspective, from an outside perspective it's visible together. But then what does
it matter whether one's on a valley or one's in a wadi
or one's on a
mountain? Right. No, but I think the fact that the גמרא Gemara
is saying that if it's on a mountain and this is somewhere
here, that that's considered נראה עמו nira imo even though it's very
distant. Right. The logical answer is that we're looking from the perspective
of the city. If we're looking from a third perspective, how does
seeing it on the mountain make these two more visible together? Right,
if anything they're more visible together if they're on the same plane.
I agree with you the language is from an outside perspective, but
the answer seems to be assume it's from the perspective of the
city. Okay, so ואמר רבי יהושע בן לוי. v'amar Rebbi Yehoshua ben
Levi. Now רבי יהושע בן לוי Rebbi Yehoshua ben Levi also says,
going back to these definitions of the city, I'm sorry, I'm talking
to myself now.
Okay, I was wondering who's making that noise. Of course it's me.
Okay, ואמר רבי יהושע בן לוי כרך וישבו ולבסוף הוקף נידון ככפר.
v'amar Rebbi Yehoshua ben Levi krach veyashevu ulebasof hukaf nidon kekfar. Now
this is if you have a כרך, krach, for now we'll read
it a walled city, that was settled and then the wall was
built. So first people started living in it and then you built
the wall afterwards. That's just like a village. That doesn't count as
a walled city. מאי טעמא? mai taama? Which means now you not
only have to know that it was walled from the time of
יהושע בן נון, Yehoshua bin Nun, but you have to know that
first the wall was built and then it was inhabited. דכתיב, dechtiv,
because the verse says by selling houses in walled cities and the
special הלכות halachot that apply to them as far as the יובל
Yovel is concerned, ואיש כי ימכר בית מושב עיר חומה. ve'ish ki
yimkor beit moshav ir choma. If a person sells a house of
settlement in a walled city. So that means it's a בית מושב
beit moshav that was in an עיר חומה, ir choma, that the
עיר חומה ir choma preceded the fact that it was a בית
מושב. beit moshav. So the גמרא Gemara is assuming, so let's assume
whatever, so that's the read of that verse. But taking that for
the read of the verse, what's interesting is the גמרא Gemara is
taking the הלכה halacha about selling houses in walled cities and applying
it to the issue of מגילה, Megillah, right? What does it have
to do? Maybe certain הלכות halachot for houses in walled cities for
laws of יובל, Yovel, what does it have to do with this
הלכה halacha about reading within a walled city or not walled city
and what the definition is? And because of this question, רש"י Rashi
sort of reads the statement that he's saying. רש"י Rashi says we're
not actually talking here now about הלכות מגילה. hilchos Megillah. We're talking
about הלכות halachot about when he says the question about was this
wall built first or whatever, the הלכה halacha is about just this
הלכה halacha about selling houses in a walled city. We're not talking
about הלכות מגילה. hilchos Megillah.
Meaning it could be either walled or settled first.
Yeah, this issue of walled or settled first is just about הלכות,
halachot, not about הלכות מגילה, hilchos Megillah, רש"י Rashi says.
For מגילה Megillah it
wouldn't matter.
Right, for מגילה Megillah it wouldn't matter. That's what רש"י Rashi says,
but it doesn't sit in the flow of the גמרא, Gemara, and
תוספות Tosafot disagree. And the way it really seems that we're dealing
with here, and this is important because it gets us to the
question of the significance of ימות יהושע בן נון, yimos Yehoshua bin
Nun, which seems to be arbitrary, is what חז"ל Chazal sometimes do
is that they take pre-existing categories, definitions, which is convenient and apply
them to new הלכות halachot even if they don't exactly match those
new הלכות. halachot. But it's easy to reuse a category. So for
example, at the beginning of גיטין Gittin you have the idea of
somebody brings a גט get from חוץ לארץ chutz l'aretz to ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, he has to say בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם, bifnai
nichtav uvifnai nechtam, he has to testify to the way it was
written because they don't necessarily know how to do the הלכות halachot
correctly outside of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. And then the גמרא Gemara
discusses what are the parameters of ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael? And it
then discusses the parameters of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael for like הלכות
תרומות ומעשרות, hilchos trumos u'maasros, of קדושת ארץ ישראל. kedushas Eretz Yisrael.
What the heck does that have to do with the areas that
know how to write a גט get correctly or not? And the
answer is it doesn't necessarily, but if there's this הלכה halacha that
deals with ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, whatever the reasons are, it might
be more convenient to just use a pre-existing definition of ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael and apply it here. And that seems to be a
little bit of what's going on. We have a definition in other
הלכות halachot of walled cities. Let's borrow that category and use that
category here for defining what constitutes a walled city. And that seems
to be what the גמרא Gemara is doing, taking something from בתי
ערי חומה batei arei choma and applying it here. And that also
therefore explains the significance of מוקף חומה מימות יהושע בן נון, mukaf
choma mi'yimos Yehoshua bin Nun, because that actually is a הלכה halacha
that is relevant to... in other areas. Number one, for example, this
thing like walled cities, but beyond this issue of houses in walled
cities, you know, if it goes by the first time that had
that status, it was when they came in at the time of
יהושע בן נון, Yehoshua Bin Nun, and maybe the קדושה ראשונה קידשה
לשעתה וקידשה לעתיד לבוא, kedusha rishona kidsha lishata vekidsha leatid lavo, etc.
So that status as when they went in יהושע בן נון Yehoshua
Bin Nun would still be relevant even by בית שני. Bayis Sheini.
But another reason that it's important is, and this is a very
little known fact, is that if you look in the beginning משניות
Mishnayot in כלים, Keilim, you see that when it lists the different
levels of קדושה kedusha ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, you know, it starts
with the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, then הר הבית, Har HaBayit, then
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and between ירושלים Yerushalayim and all the rest of ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, you know what comes as a middle status? Yes,
walled cities from the time of יהושע בן נון. Yehoshua Bin Nun.
So and their status is something that basically like the גמרא Gemara
says they're considered מחנה ישראל. machaneh Yisrael. The same way the תורה
Torah says you send out of the מחנה, machaneh, you know, the
מצורעים, metzora'im, you send them not only outside of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, but
you send them outside of the walled cities. So a walled city
as a city, not just a house in a walled city, has
a הלכה. halacha. But the whole status of the identity of the
city as some special status is a pre-existing הלכה halacha that applies
to walled cities from the time of יהושע בן נון. Yehoshua Bin
Nun. So I actually think that that is what is going on
about this arbitrary assignment of ימות יהושע בן נון Yemos Yehoshua Bin
Nun as opposed to ימות אחשורוש. Yemos Achashverosh. So I'll give you,
I'll say other reasons later, but I think that that's really what
we see in these next couple of הלכות, halachos, the drawing on
other categories to apply to the definition of walled city here by
מגילה. Megilla. Yes, David.
And maybe another point that can help us understand why walled cities
should have a special status. Right?
Starting in the חומש, Chumash,
cities have really bad press. Cities play bad roles.
That's a fascinating point. You know, it's a very interesting point. I
assumed it was because walled cities have well-defined demarcations and sort of
like the idea of a מחנה ישראל machaneh Yisrael and a mini
מחנה machaneh when you transfer that idea to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
you know, as opposed to villages there's no like demarcating line. But
that's a very interesting insight. All right, so for some other time.
All right, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay.
So where are we?
Okay. שהוקף ולבסוף ישב. shehukaf ulevasof yashav. Okay. ובאם בבית מושב עיר
חומה שהוקף ולבסוף ישב, uve'im bevait moshav ir chomah shehukaf ulevasof yashav,
first you have an עיר חומה ir chomah and then it was
settled ולא שישב ולבסוף הוקף. velo sheyashav ulevasof hukaf. And that's by
houses in walled cities and therefore presumably according to תוספות Tosafot at
least that's the same by
מגילה. Megilla. ואמר רבי יהושע בן לוי כרך שאין בו עשרה בטלנים
נידון ככפר. Ve'amar Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Levi krach she'ein bo asara batlanim
nidon kekfar.
Now if a כרך, krach, again we'll say it means a walled
city, doesn't have ten בטלנים, batlanim, ten people that are just sitting
around doing nothing, meaning so the idea of like somebody as a
מנין minyan man and available for making a מנין, minyan, this was
an idea already in the גמרא, Gemara, people that would be basically
be present to, you know, in some communal capacity and always available,
that's called the עשרה בטלנים. asara batlanim. So נידון ככפר, nidon kekfar,
if it doesn't have those people, then it's not big enough to
be considered a כרך krach and it's only a village. Now at
presumably this means even if it is a wall from the time
of יהושע בן נון, Yehoshua Bin Nun, which is a fascinating new
criteria. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי קא משמע לן, mai ka
mashma lan, where do you learn this? דתנינא, detanina, we taught it,
I mean what is this teaching us? We've already taught, which is
coming up later in משנה, mishnah, איזו היא עיר גדולה כל שיש
בה עשרה בטלנים, eizu hi ir gedola kol sheyesh bah asara batlanim,
if it has ten בטלנים, batlanim, it's a משנה mishnah coming up,
פחות מכאן הרי זה כפר, pachos mikan harei zeh kefar, less than
that it's a village. So the גמרא Gemara says no, כרך איצטריכא
ליה. krach itztricha lei. No, you need to tell me that it
is true even in the case not just of a big city
but of a כרך, krach, of like a of a metropolis or
of a walled city. אף על גב, Af al gav, because what
would I say? I would say well you've got like a big
town, an עיר ir more often is a town than a city,
right? A כפר kefar is a village, an עיר ir is a
town, and a כרך krach is a city. Okay, so if you
have a city that, so city has a lot of people coming
in from outside, אף על גב דמקלעו ליה מעלמא, af al gav
demiklu lei me'alma, so although you have an enormous amount of foot
traffic and people are coming from outside that,
and you might think that you don't need עשרה בטלנים asara batlanim
because like you'll never have a problem, you know, making a מנין
minyan or you'll never have a problem of getting enough people because
there's so much, you know, you know, there's so much
ingress, that maybe the you don't need עשרה בטלנים asara batlanim and
it always has an important status. It says no, even that you
need עשרה בטלנים. asara batlanim. Now the question here is what do
you need the what status what do you need the עשרה בטלנים
asara batlanim for? When the משנה mishnah later says to be an
עיר גדולה, ir gedola, it needs עשרה בטלנים asara batlanim or if
not it's a כפר, kefar, what what's the significance of being an
עיר גדולה? ir gedola? Do you remember what we taught in the
first משנה mishnah as opposed to a כפר kefar as opposed to
a village?
Right? What happens the עיירות, ayarot, the... what... בשבת המקדימין? bashabbat hamakdimin?
Yeah but what's the הלכה halacha difference? Right? What does the משנה
mishnah say? There's three things in the משנה. mishnah. There's מוקף חומה,
mukaf chomah, right? And there's כפרים kfarim and there's עיירות גדולות. ayarot
gedolot. Right? So a כפר kefar reads when?
Monday market day. עיירות גדולות *ayarot gedolot* always read on the right
day, unless there's a שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* problem. So what this משנה
Mishnah, *Mishnah* later is saying is to determine are you a village
or an עיר גדול *ir gadol* where you'd be pushed back to
a market day or do you read on the right day? If
you don't have עשרה בטלנים asara batlanim *asarah batlanim* then you're not
a big enough, you know, town to be an עיר גדול *ir
gadol*. You are just a כפר *kfar* and you're going to get
pushed back. That's what it says.
So the question is, is the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* now saying that
that's also what's required even if you have a wall from the
time of יהושע בן נון Yehoshua bin Nun. *Yehoshua bin Nun*, you
need עשרה בטלנים asara batlanim. *asarah batlanim*? So תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* says
no, that's going too far, because you've got a wall from the
time of יהושע בן נון Yehoshua bin Nun? *Yehoshua bin Nun*, that's
enough to give it significance and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* would have
mentioned that explicitly. And תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* wants to say that what
this means is even if you have a walled city, not has
a wall from the time of יהושע בן נון Yehoshua bin Nun
*Yehoshua bin Nun*. You have a metropolis, you have a large city,
it's got a wall, just not יהושע Yehoshua בן נון *Yehoshua bin
Nun*, and still the question for תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* is not whether
you're a 15 or a 14, whether you're a walled city that
reads on the 15th or not that reads on the 14th. He
says the issue even by the walled city here is a non,
not a wall from יהושע Yehoshua. *Yehoshua*, and the question is even
with that wall, are you you're not necessarily significant enough to read
on the 14th if you don't have עשרה asara, בטלנים *asarah batlanim*.
Okay, so this is this is a little bit confusing because it
uses the word כרך krach *krach* and until now כרך krach *krach*
has been the question of the status of a walled city to
read on the 15th, which is a way to read this גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*. It's probably the פשט *pshat* way to read this גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* that it's not enough that it has a wall, it
also needs עשרה בטלנים *asarah batlanim*. The same way an עיר *ir*
needs עשרה בטלנים *asarah batlanim*, a כרך *krach* needs עשרה בטלנים *asarah
batlanim*. But תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* does not want to read it that
way. תוספות *Tosafos* wants to say we're dealing with a non-wall, a
wall not from יהושע Yehoshua. *Yehoshua*, and still the issue is whether
it has the status as an עיר *ir* or not. Yes.
So what we're looking at is it seems like the real the
real matter was if you're not big enough you're not going to
have someone able to read the מגילה Megillah, *Megillah* so you've got
to go to the big city.
I know but again
well that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, that's the חידוש *chiddush*,
that's קא משמע לן *kama mashma lan*. Alright, I don't want to
belabor, we've got to move on. ואמר רבי יהושע בן לוי ve-amar
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. כרך שחרב ולסוף ישב נידון ככרך *Ve-amar Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi, krach she-charav u-le-sof yashav nidun ke-krach*. If a כרך
*krach* was destroyed
and then resettled it has the status of a כרך *krach*. So
the גמרא Gemara's *Gemara* says מאי חרב *mai charav*? What does it
mean it was destroyed? אילימא חרבו חומותיו *Ileima charvu chomotav*, that the
walls were knocked down, people were still living there, the walls were
knocked down and then they were rebuilt. So ישב אין לא ישב
לא *yashav in lo yashav lo*? So it only has a status
if it's if the walls are rebuilt? והתניא *Ve-ha tanyeh*, we learned
in a ברייתא *Beraita*, רבי אליעזר בן רבי יוסי אומר *Rabbi Eliezer
ben Rabbi Yose omer*, אשר לו חומה *asher lo chomah*, that it
has a wall. This is again selling houses in places with a
walled city. So there's a little question here the way it's read
or written. Is it read לו *lo* that with a ו *vav*
that it has a wall or לא *lo* חומה *chomah* that it
doesn't have a wall? So he says you read it both ways.
אף af על פי שאין לו עכשיו *Af al pi she-ein lo
achshav*, even if there's no wall now, והיה לו קודם לכן *ve-hayah
lo kodem lachem*, as long as it initially had a wall it's
considered to be a house in a walled city. So again notice
because for the laws of houses in a walled city it's enough
that it once had a wall, even though it doesn't have a
wall now, the same will be true by walled cities for מגילה
Megillah, *Megillah*. So why would you say that the wall was knocked
down and rebuilt? Even if it wasn't rebuilt, if it once had
that wall that would be enough. Again borrowing a category from houses
in the walled city for the laws of like יובל *Yovel* and
applying it to מגילה Megillah, *Megillah*. You don't need it to have
a walled city now, which by the way is important, right? Because
then it means that on the one hand we can't assume that
anything that's a walled city now reads on the 15th because the
question is was it from the time of יהושע בן נון *Yehoshua
bin Nun*. But we also can't assume that anything that's not a
walled city now doesn't read on the 15th because it might have
had a wall that was knocked down, right? And there's definitely ancient
cities, right, that had walls and they were knocked down and they
might read on the 15th. Okay, so again borrowing from the laws
of בתי ערי חומה *batei arei chomah*, we say it doesn't need
the wall to be rebuilt. So what would need to be rebuilt
for it to regain the status? אלא מאי חרב *Ella mai charav*?
שחרב מעשרה בטלנים *She-charav me-asarah batlanim*. Back to this idea. It had
ten בטלנים *batlanim*, then it stopped, so it loses its status, whether
status of a 15 or status of a 14, that's the issue
I mentioned before. When it regains the עשרה בטלנים *asarah batlanim* it'll
regain the status. Okay. So what have we introduced? We've introduced the
idea that for two things from בתי ערי חומה *batei arei chomah*,
number one is it has to first have made the wall and
then be settled. Number two it doesn't need the wall right now.
And it seems that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying we're just
going to borrow those definitions from בתי ערי חומה *batei arei chomah*
and apply them to the הלכה halakha *halakhah* of reading on the
15th. And I included in that well the idea of borrowing where
I think is why we get the basic idea of walls from
the time of יהושע בן נון *Yehoshua bin Nun*. The other issue
that's quite clear we introduced is עשרה בטלנים *asarah batlanim*, which might
be a criteria to read on the 15th, might be only a
criteria to read on the 14th. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
goes on, ואמר רבי יהושע בן לוי v'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi
*ve-amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi*. Now we're going to start a lot
of statements of רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, *Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi* all around מגילה Megillah. *Megillah*. And now we're going
to start listing talking about specific cities. לוד Lod. ואונו וגיא החרשים
*Lod ve-Ono ve-Gai ha-Charashim*, these three cities, מוקפות חומה מימות יהושע בן
נון הוו *mukafot chomah mi-yemot Yehoshua bin Nun havu*. They were these
were all cities mentioned in the פסוקים psukim *psukim* by in שבט
בנימין Binyamin, *shevet Binyamin* and he had a... And he had a
tradition that all of these were walled from the time of יהושע
בן נון. והא, Ve-ha, so the גמרא Gemara says, והני יהושע בנינו?
Ve-hani Yehoshua beninu? One minute, יהושע built those walls?
והא אלפאעל בנינו! Ve-ha Elpa'el beninu! דכתיב ובני אלפאעל עבר ומשעם ושמר
הוא בנה את אונו ואת לוד ובנותיה. dikhtiv u-vnei Elpa'el Ever u-Misham
ve-Shemer hu bana et Ono ve-et Lod u-vnotieha. He, or you know,
אלפאעל Elpa'el or אלפאעל Elpa'el's children built אונו Ono and לוד. So
two of the three cities. So what? Yes,
and he's a lot later than יהושע. This was in the time
of the פילגש בגבעה. pilegesh be-Giv'ah. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
so at least two of them were built later than יהושע. So
the גמרא Gemara says וטעמיך u-taimekh one minute, according to that you
think oh look, אלפאעל Elpa'el built it? I'll tell you a third
person built it. אסא בנינהו, Asa beninhu, אסא Asa built it. דכתיב
dikhtiv it says ויבן, va-yiven, and our גמרא Gemara says אסא, Asa,
it's ערי המצורות אשר ליהודה, arei ha-metzurot asher li-Yehudah, but that is
not in the verse, the verse is if you look at the
side, ויבן ערי מצורה, va-yiven arei metzurah, is it מצודה? metzudah?
מצודה? Metzudah? No, מצורה. metzurah. Yeah I think, like בצורות. betzurot. מצורה
ביהודה. metzurah bi-Yehudah. Anyway, but the גמרא Gemara stuck in the word
אסא Asa because that is the clear actor in the verse even
though it's not in the verse itself. So anyway, so he built
them. Now exactly how we know that it's talking about, about what
do you call it, about these cities.
רש״י Rashi says,
רש״י Rashi says that it's clear from the context that these are
cities that are in בנימין, Binyamin although it says ערי יהודה, arei
Yehudah, and it's assuming if it's in בנימין Binyamin, it includes all
of these cities. Again, though it's not as specific as the previous
verse, but anyway, that's the גמרא Gemara question. If he built up
the walls of all of these cities in יהודה Yehudah and בנימין,
Binyamin then he built them, so it's not אלפאעל. Elpa'el. So the
גמרא Gemara says, so אמר רבי אלעזר, amar Rabbi Elazar, so רבי
אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says not all true. הני מוקפות חומה מימות יהושע
בן נון הוו, hani mukafot choma mi-yemot Yehoshua bin Nun havu, they
really were, had a wall in the time of יהושע בן נון.
חרבו בימי פילגש בגבעה, charavu bi-ymei pilegesh be-Giv'ah, in the time of
פילגש בגבעה pilegesh be-Giv'ah where they, you know, basically decimated בנימין and
destroyed all the cities, so the walls were knocked down in the
time of פילגש בגבעה. pilegesh be-Giv'ah. ואתא אלפאעל בנינהו האי, ve-ata Elpa'el
beninhu hai, and then אלפאעל Elpa'el came and rebuilt those walls that
were destroyed in the time of פילגש בגבעה. pilegesh be-Giv'ah. הדר אינפול,
hadar inful, then they started crumbling, they weren't completely destroyed, but they
started, you know, over time crumbling. ואתא אסא שפינהו, ve-ata Asa shafinhu,
and אסא Asa came and he sort of fixed them up, he
improved them. Okay, so all three are true. דיקנא נמי דכתיב, dikna
nami dikhtiv, it also works with the verse says, ויאמר ליהודה נבנה
את הערים האלה. va-yomer li-Yehudah nivneh et he-arim ha-eleh. So he, אסא
Asa said to יהודה, Yehudah, let's build up these cities. מכלל דערים
הוו מעיקרא, mikhlal de-arim havu me-ikara, they were already cities, and he
was just putting up the walls. Now it doesn't mean they might
have been cities without any walls, but anyway the גמרא Gemara, is
saying they already had some wall, he was just improving it. Okay,
שמע מינה. shema mina. Again, what's not answered is what do you
do if you don't have a tradition? What do you do if
it has a wall, you don't know if it's time of יהושע
בן נון? You know it's from the time of יהושע בן נון
but you don't know what are the... you don't know if it
was first the wall was made and then it was settled, or
it was settled and then the wall was made, right? How do
you deal with these areas of doubt? Do you sort of assume
that everything is on the 14th unless you can prove otherwise? Or
do you assume that no, once there's a certain doubt raised then
you have to read both on the 14th and the 15th, right?
So these are very important הלכה halakha questions. The other important הלכה
halakha question which I mentioned yesterday ties into ישוב הנראה וסמוך yishuv
ha-nireh ve-samukh is let's say you have a continuous buildup of a
city like ירושלים, Yerushalayim, right? I mean, you know, how much of
ירושלים Yerushalayim is the walled city of ירושלים? Yerushalayim? But not all
of it is סמוך ונראה samukh ve-nireh to the walled city. Right,
but if it's a continuous buildup, you know, then maybe it just
continues to get that הלכה halacha, as well. So a lot of
these are very relevant questions. Yes.
You can be found for three categories, architectural, sociology, and historical status.
What
do
you mean by sociology, you mean like the עשרה בטלנים or?
Well, it could be עשרה, yes, but the way that a walled
city operates has to be different, you see people actually build their
homes into walls.
Right. The responsibility of people to the polity was different in a
walled city than in other places. But the question really just pulls
out here consistently, like what are they trying to get at?
Right.
So the גמרא Gemara will get to that a little bit later
when it will see when it deals with some questions of exactly
what constitutes a wall.
So let's hold off on that, okay? Right now we sort of...
what right now what I'm seeing is a formalistic borrowing from other
categories, but there it also could be questions about what actually are
the sort of issues that are at stake here as well, and
that we'll, we'll see as we continue. Okay, so not today, but
in a soon. Okay, so the גמרא tells like this, okay, ואמר
רבי יהושע בן לוי. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi Again רבי יהושע בן
לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi.
very famous statement that appears in a couple of contexts, נשים חייבות
במקרא מגילה, nashim chayavot be-mikra megillah, women are obligated in the reading
of the מגילה, Megillah, שאף הן היו באותו הנס, she-af hen hayu
be-oto ha-nes,
that even they were in that miracle. Although it's a זמן גרמא
מצוה zman gerama mitzvah and you would say normally women would be
exempt, here they're obligated because even they were in the miracle. Now
there's two questions about this. Well actually there's three, one specific to
מגילה, Megillah but ending. In general about this statement. Number one is
what the phrase of אף הן היו באותו הנס af hen hayu
be'oto hanes means. Does it mean that they were saved by the
miracle, which is they would have been wiped out by פורים? Purim?
This is also used by חנוכה Chanukah to say that חנוכה Chanukah
women are obligated אף הן היו באותו הנס af hen hayu be'oto
hanes because similarly they were under the same edict at the time
of חנוכה. Chanukah. And it's used by—the other thing it's used by
though is the ארבע כוסות. arba kosot. So and they were saved
by the time of יציאת מצרים. Yetzias Mitzrayim. So women were always
sort of in the category of those that were part of the
miracle, included in the miracle. Of course if you raise that, then
it's true about everything. It's true about סוכה, Sukkah, it's true about
why don't they have to take ציצית? tzitzit? Why don't they take
לולב? Lulav? Right? So what's specific about that that it's דווקא davka
the three applications that exist in the גמרא which is חנוכה, Chanukah,
פורים, Purim, and the ארבע כוסות? arba kosot? I'm going to come
back to that, but I will tell you there is an alternate
read of this, which is the רשב"ם, Rashbam, which doesn't just mean
that they were included in those that were saved by the miracle,
but that they were centrally instrumental in the miracle
because it
says by—and now this isn't—so if you take a look like תוספות
has it where let me just see תוספות to אף הן היו
באותו הנס. af hen hayu be'oto hanes. He says פירוש רשב"ם שעיקר
הנס היה על ידן, peirush Rashbam she'ikar hanes haya al yadan, the
פורים Purim was על ידי אסתר, al yedei Esther, so that's an
easy one, וחנוכה על ידי יהודית, veChanukah al yedei Yehudit, the story
about יהודית Yehudit and who fed the whatever, sort of like a
יעל Yael story
there, ובפסח שבזכות נשים צדקניות שבאותו הדור נגאלו, uv'Pesach shebizchut nashim tzidkaniyot
shebe'oto hador nig'alu, the famous גמרא that it was because of the
righteous women. וקשה ללשון שאף הן, v'kashe l'lashon she'af hen, משמע שהן
טפלות. mashma shehen tefeilot. Now it sounds like they were like secondary,
not primary. Now, you could take it means that they were also
instrumental. Being instrumental is not necessarily the same as being primarily, but
okay, but if the way the רשב"ם Rashbam wanted to read it,
which is that they were like the primary sort of reason for
the גאולה, geulah, the question of אף af is a little bit
of a challenge. Again, I don't think it's such a big deal.
אף הן היו af hen hayu could be they were also instrumental
as opposed to they were also saved by the miracle. There are
other ways of trying to deal with the אף phrase according to
the רשב"ם. Rashbam. So that's just a question of what that means.
But then we turn to the issue about why specifically these three?
Which is particularly of question if it just means that they were
redeemed, right? Why specifically מגילה, Megillah חנוכה, Chanukah, and the ארבע כוסות?
arba kosot? And the ארבע כוסות arba kosot is particularly a challenge
because we don't use the principle of אף הן היו באותו הנס
af hen hayu be'oto hanes to explain that women should be obligated
to eat מצה matzah or to eat מרור, maror, right? That comes
from some other דרשה, drasha, from some other explanation. So why specifically
these three? So the first thing that these three shares is that
they're all רבנן. rabbanan. So that's one answer that sort of תוספות
says, which is this principle of אף הן היו באותו הנס af
hen hayu be'oto hanes to include women is basically a רבנן rabbanan
principle. It's not biblical. So if you want to make women biblically
obligated in מצה, matzah, you have to do it from another direction.
This is רבנן rabbanan and therefore this is the principle that's used
to include them in these רבנן מצוות. rabbanan mitzvot. So that's one
reason why it sort of focuses on those. And therefore maybe you
could say things like
סוכה, Sukkah, which is not רבנן, rabbanan, we don't want to be
using this principle. This principle we only want to use in sort
of by רבנן מצוות. rabbanan mitzvot. הרב סולובייצ'יק, HaRav Soloveitchik, however, gives
an answer which is I think a much more satisfying one. And
he says that the idea of נס nes is a very central
idea in terms of the מצוה mitzvah of מגילה. Megillah We just
used a phrase before to describe the central weight of the מצוה
mitzvah of מגילה, Megillah which is what? פרסומי ניסא. pirsumei nisa. What
was the idea of פרסומי ניסא? pirsumei nisa? פרסומי ניסא pirsumei nisa
is you want to make sure that everybody participates because by everybody's
participation, it highlights the publicizing of the miracle. So the כהנים kohanim
leave the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, the ישיבה בחורים yeshiva bachurim leave
the בית המדרש. Beis HaMedrash. Everybody comes because of פרסומי ניסא. pirsumei
nisa. So he says these מצוות mitzvot are the specific מצוות—let's mitzvot
first talk about the first two, which are the more obvious: חנוכה
Chanukah and פורים. Purim. How do I know that מקרא מגילה mikra
Megillah and lighting חנוכה Chanukah candles have a specific identity as מצוות
של פרסום הנס mitzvos shel pirsum hanes that other מצוות mitzvot don't
have? Because those are the two מצוות mitzvot that you make the
ברכה bracha of שעשה נסים. she'asa nissim. You never make that ברכה
bracha by any other מצוה. mitzvah. And therefore those two מצוות, mitzvot,
the whole one major part of their identity is you are lighting
the נרות חנוכה neiros Chanukah so everybody sees it's done for the
sake of פרסומי ניסא. pirsumei nisa. You're reading the מגילה Megillah to
be מפרסם. mefarsem. Obviously, if you're alone, you light חנוכה Chanukah also
and you read מגילה Megillah also, but a central part of the
מצוה mitzvah is the fact that it is achieving פרסומי ניסא. pirsumei
nisa. So if the goal is פרסומי ניסא, pirsumei nisa, you want
as many people involved in the מצוה mitzvah as possible. And women—another
way: if women were part of the נס nes and this whole
thing is about the נס, nes, then women do it as well.
So it's both because it focuses on the נס nes and women
were in the נס, nes, and because it focuses on the נס
nes and therefore you want it to be מפרסם. mefarsem. So both
the נס nes and the פרסומי pirsumei explain why you want to
be including women. The ארבע כוסות arba kosot similarly is something that
is done just for the sake of demonstrating
that you are בני חורין. bnei chorin. Eating the מצה, matzah, eating
the מרור, maror, that... Those are not necessarily
done, it's done, it's in the תורה Torah, *Torah*, it might be
to remember what happened, but like the act of eating מצה *matzah*
is not necessarily an act of demonstrating you're בני חורין *bnei chorin*.
The drinking of the wine and the ארבע כוסות *arba kosos* and
the reclining, that is more the demonstrating of בני חורין *bnei chorin*
and that again is a פרסום הנס *pirsum hanes* type of an
act. Right. Right.
But what is the נס nes *nes* for פורים Purim *Purim*? Why
do we have to have a supernatural event? Right, right. But what
is the
נס nes *nes*?
So it's a נס נסתר *nes nistar*. So that's the whole story
of פורים Purim *Purim*, that God's name isn't there, but it's still
attached to the נס *nes*, right? That's the point. You can be
מפרסם *mefarsem* a נס נסתר *nes nistar*.
Right, so wouldn't you want to do the same thing for women
too?
So wouldn't we want the women to sit there? Yeah, so that's
a good point, but it's not as much to be מפרסם *mefarsem*
to others as more understood as you're sitting and you're remembering as
opposed to the sort of larger public. Okay, so that, oh, last
thing to say about women, חיי *chai*, what you can't not discuss
in this context is the practical הלכה *halacha*, not just this broad
principle but the practical הלכה *halacha* of women's obligation in מגילה Megillah,
*Megilla*. Are women equally obligated, could they be מוציא *motzi* men? So
let's take a look at תוספות *Tosafot*. נשים חייבות במקרא מגילה Megillah
*Nashim chayavot bemikra Megilla*. This is obviously an important discussion that comes
up around פורים Purim. *Purim* time. מכאן משמע שנשים מוציאות את האחרים
ידי חובתן *Mikan mashma she'nashim motzi'ot et ha'acherim yedei chovatan*, that women
are equally obligated and can read מגילה Megillah, *Megilla* for others, for
men meaning. מדלא קאמר לשמוע מקרא מגילה mikra Megillah, *Mide'lo ka'amar lishmo'a
mikra Megilla*, doesn't say they're obligated to hear, which is a way
of formulating a different level of obligation. No, they're obligated to read
so they can read for others. והכי נמי מתני בערכין *Ve'hachi nami
masna be'Arachin* דקאמר הכל כשירים לקרות את המגילה *de'ka'amar hakol kshairim likros
et ha'Megilla* ומצי הכל כשירים לאתויי מאי ומשני לאתויי נשים *u'matzi hakol
kshairim la'atuyei mai u'shani la'atuyei nashim*. So everybody's obligated, sounds like equal
obligation, including women. משמע להוציא אפילו אנשים *Mashma lehotzi afilu anashim*. Okay,
and that is the way many, many ראשונים *Rishonim* פוסקן *pasken*. Women
are equally obligated, they could read for men. But now תוספות *Tosafot*
has a problem based on הלכות halakhot גדולות *Hilchos Gedolos* and based
on a תוספתא *Tosefta*. דקשיא דהא בתוספתא תני בהדיא דטומטום אין מוציא
לא מינו ולא שאינו מינו *Dekashya de'ha bitosefta tani behedya de'tumtum ein
motzi lo mino velo she'eino mino*. A טומטום *tumtum*, who we don't
know if he's male or female, can't be מוציא *motzi* another טומטום
*tumtum* because maybe טומטום *tumtum* number one is a female and טומטום
*tumtum* number two is a male and therefore a טומטום *tumtum* can't
be מוציא *motzi* another טומטום *tumtum* because you don't know if someone's
genitalia is covered up and you don't know if it's male or
female. So that seems to be clear that women can't be מוציא
*motzi* men, although it never says that, but that seems to be
the problem of the טומטום *tumtum*. So then he says וכן פסק
*vechen pasak*, I'm skipping a little word there, וכן פסק הלכות גדולות
*vechen pasak Hilchos Gedolos* דאשה מוציאה מינה *de'isha motzi'a mina*, a woman
could be מוציא *motzi* a woman, אבל לא אנשים *aval lo anashim*,
but not men. Okay. And then he says, so okay, so maybe
that's the way to read all these גמרות *Gemaras* that say women
are obligated, maybe it means obligated but at a different level, obligated
so that they can be מוציא *motzi* women, not obligated to be
מוציא *motzi* men. And one way of framing it is that they're
obligated to hear but they're not obligated to read, so it's a
different type of an obligation. So based on this תוספתא *Tosefta*, the
הלכות גדולות *Hilchos Gedolos* comes to a conclusion that women's obligation is
different than men and women can't be מוציא *motzi* men, but that's
against the simple read of the גמרא *Gemara* and many, many ראשונים
*Rishonim*. But some, a lot of ראשוני אשכנז *Rishonei Ashkenaz* follow תוספות
*Tosafot*, follow הלכות גדולות *Hilchos Gedolos*, and that leads to these issues
about women reading the מגילה Megillah *Megilla* for men. Okay, so now
let's get back to the גמרא *Gemara*. Okay, a lot we're covering,
a lot of ground we're covering. Well, a lot of conceptual ground,
I don't know, a lot of גמרא *Gemara* ground. Okay. ואמר רבי
יהושע בן לוי *Ve'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi*, רבי יהושע בן לוי
*Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi* also said פורים Purim. שחל
להיות בשבת שואלין ודורשין בעניינו של יום *Purim she'chal lihyot be'Shabbos sho'alin
ve'dorshin be'inyano shel yom*. If פורים Purim. *Purim* falls out on שבת
Shabbos. *Shabbos*, even though you're not going to read the מגילה Megillah.
*Megilla*, you have an obligation instead of reading the מגילה Megillah, *Megilla*
to teach and talk about the issues relating to פורים *Purim*. And
רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* specifically says it's not just הלכות פורים halachos Purim
*hilchos Purim*, but רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says it's expounding on the מגילה
Megillah *Megilla* itself. You have to give a שיעור *shiur* on the
מגילה Megillah *Megilla* when פורים *Purim* falls out on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*
as in the substitute for actually reading the מגילה Megillah *Megilla*. So
the גמרא *Gemara* says מאי איריא פורים *mai irya Purim*, what's the
חידוש פורים *chidush Purim*? אפילו יום טוב נמי *afilu Yom Tov nami*,
even on יום טוב *Yom Tov*. דתניא *Detanya*, we talked about in
a ברייתא *braitah*, משה תיקן להם לישראל שיהיו שואלין ודורשין בעניינו של
יום *Moshe tikken lahem le'Yisrael she'yehu sho'alin ve'dorshin be'inyano shel yom*, that
you have to talk about the aspects of the חג *chag* on
the חג *chag*. הלכות פסח בפסח הלכות עצרת בעצרת הלכות חג בחג
*Hilchos Pesach be'Pesach, hilchos Atzeres be'Atzeres, hilchos chag be'chag*. So now, it's
not clear why just because you do it for a יום טוב
*Yom Tov* you should do it for פורים *Purim*. So תוספות *Tosafot*
says no, here's the point. Because for a יום טוב *Yom Tov*,
not only are we saying you're supposed to talk about it on
יום טוב *Yom Tov*, what's the other הלכה *halacha* we say about
יום טוב *Yom Tov*? Right, you're supposed to begin talking about the
הלכות שלשים יום לפני החג *halachos shloshim yom lifnei hachag*. So if
by יום טוב *Yom Tov*, when you started talking about it for
a month ago, you've been talking about it now and you still
are supposed to talk about it on the יום *yom* itself. So
certainly פורים *Purim*, which we don't start talking about הלכות פורים *hilchos
Purim* a month before פורים *Purim*, certainly פורים *Purim*, all you have
is the day itself, you certainly need to be talking about it
on פורים *Purim* itself. So what's the חידוש *chidush*? Of course you
have to talk about פורים *Purim* on פורים *Purim* itself. So the
גמרא *Gemara* says no, פורים איצטריך ליה *Purim itztrich lei*, there's still
a חידוש *chidush* by פורים *Purim*. מהו דתימא ניגזר משום דרבה *Mahu
detaima nigzar mishum de'Rabbah*, I might think you're not allowed to give
a שיעור *shiur* on מגילה Megillah *Megilla* on פורים *Purim* that falls
on שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*, why? Because if you start דרשנ'ינג darshaning *darshaning*
מגילה Megillah, then you'll come to take out your מגילה Megillah and
you come to carry your מגילה Megillah and maybe the same reason
that רבה Rabbah explains why you don't read the מגילה Megillah on
שבת is because you might come to carry it, maybe you shouldn't
give a דרשה drasha on the מגילה Megillah on שבת. קמשמע לן
Kamashmalan that that's not such a concern, that it's you have to,
you know, you have to read, so, you know, you have to
take the מגילה, Megillah, I don't know why it's not, logically the
difference is not so clear, but, you know, it requires more of
an expert to read, so you would bring your מגילה Megillah to
an expert to read it, whereas hearing a דרשה drasha you just
show up and you just listen. I'm not exactly sure because, you
know, also one person giving the דרשה drasha and one person reading
the מגילה, Megillah but anyway, so we're not going to be worried
about that. We're only going to be worried about reading the מגילה
Megillah and not about giving a דרשה drasha of the מגילה. Megillah
So that is an interesting idea, and by the way, it also
does touch a little bit on the פרסומי ניסא pirsumei nisa because
the basic point here is is that reading of the מגילה, Megillah
right, is the act of being מפרסם הנס. mefarsim hanes. So then
the question becomes, well, when you don't read the מגילה Megillah on
the right day, so you can say, okay, you do the פרסומי
ניסא pirsumei nisa on an earlier day, on a Monday, on a
Thursday, on an ערב שבת Erev Shabbos whenever you do it. But
the idea of underscoring not only are you not concerned that you'll
come to carry on שבת but you need to replace the reading
of the מגילה Megillah with some type of a דרשה drasha about
the מגילה Megillah seems again to some degree at least to be
connected to this idea of פרסומי ניסא. pirsumei nisa. Okay, ואמר רבי
יהושע בן לוי and רבי יהושע בן לוי also says, this is
also a very important הלכה, a lot of very important הלכות פורים
come from רבי יהושע בן לוי. חייב אדם לקרות את המגילה בלילה
ולשנותה ביום, chayav adam likros es haMegillah balayla ulishnosah bayom,
a person has to read the מגילה Megillah at night and repeat
it in the day. שנאמר, Shene'emar, אלהי אקרא יומם, Elokai ekra yomam,
God
I will call out to you in the day, ולא תענה, v'lo
ta'aneh, and you but you don't answer, ולילה ולא דומיה לי, v'layla
v'lo dumiyah li, and even at night and I will not be
silent. So that's so now how that's exactly relating to the מגילה,
Megillah okay, so first of all, that's a פסוק pasuk by the
למנצח על אילת השחר Lamenatze'ach al Ayelet HaShachar which is understood to
be a מזמור תהלים mizmor Tehillim that relates to
אסתר. Esther. But again, the idea of like calling out, you know,
in sort of in like prayer God save me, touches on the
theme of פורים that like preceded the נס פורים, nes Purim, right?
And if you look at רש"י, Rashi רש"י Rashi says אקרא, ekra,
about 10 lines before the lines get wide, במזמור למנצח על אילת
השחר הוא שנאמר על אסתר כדאמרינן Bemizmor Lamenatze'ach al Ayelet HaShachar hu
shene'emar al Esther kedamrinan etc., מסכת יומא, Masechet Yoma,
no, no, no, there was another רש"י I wanted to read you,
oh yeah, ולשנותה ביום, ulishnosah bayom, the רש"י before that, זכר לנס
שהיו זועקים בימי צרתם יום
ולילה. zeicher lanes shehayu zoakim bimei tzarasam yom valayla. So an interesting
way using this פסוק pasuk that sort of frames the מגילה Megillah
in terms of the crying out. You only really appreciate the נס
if you appreciate the צרה tzara that they were in. So the
פסוק pasuk used to indicate the reading of the מגילה Megillah is
the פסוק pasuk about calling out to God. So that's quite interesting.
The focus on the נס really is appreciated by the focus on
the צרה tzara that preceded it. And from this פסוק pasuk we
learn you have to do it day and night.
Yes, I've been waiting for something like this. When you said earlier
that you teach from נ"ך, Nach, aren't you just proving something? Seems
like נ"ך Nach is used all the time.
Not מצוות mitzvot in the תורה, Torah,
right?
So you're right, meaning I did say right, when
if you use a פסוק pasuk in תנ"ך Tanach to prove something
in the תורה, the גמרא will say, you know, and before יחזקאל
Yechezkel came, like מי אמרה, mi amrah, you know, when like we
had that recently? And it said, well, it must have been that
it was a tradition and יחזקאל Yechezkel came and he was put
it on a פסוק. pasuk. So this is talking about like something
in, I mean, I'd be curious just to hear about like what
you're thinking about in terms of using a פסוק pasuk to prove
for a דאורייתא d'oraisa purpose because usually that's problematized. Here it's done
for more like for a דרבנן drabbanan or for a אסמכתא, asmuchta,
but yeah, but it is true, meaning the point I was making
before that we're דרשנינג darshaning פסוקים psukim of the מגילה Megillah is
not totally contrary because we're דרשנינג פסוקים psukim. about a post-biblical מצוה.
mitzvah. So it doesn't really violate the principle that you don't use
נ"ך Nach to teach you a דאורייתא, d'oraisa, but still the methodology
is the same. Okay, so now the גמרא continues.
Okay, so סברו מינה, savru minah, when people heard this דרשה drasha
that you have to read it at night ולשנותה ביום ulishnosah bayom
and to repeat it in the day, well the word לשנותה lishnosah
has a very specific meaning in the sort of in the rabbinic
society, right? משנה, Mishnah ולשנותה. ulishnosah. So סברו מינה, savru minei, when
people heard this דרשה, drasha, right, they thought, נקראוה בלילה, nikrevah balayla,
we'll read it at night, ונימני מתניתא דיומא, v'nimni masnisa d'yomah,
and we'll learn the משניות Mishnaios of מגילה Megillah, in the day.
לשנותה, Lishnosah, to do משניות Mishnaios of מגילה, Megillah to do a
type of rabbinic learning in the day. So אמר להו רבי ירמיה,
amar lehu Rabbi Yirmiyah, so רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah said to them,
no, לדידי מפרשא לי מיניה דרבי חייא בר אבא, lidi di mefarsha
li minei d'Rabbi Chiya bar Abba, no, it was explained to me
from רבי חייא בר אבא, Rabbi Chiya bar Abba, that's not what
he meant. He meant כגון דאמרי אינשי, kigone d'amri inshi, every פרשה
דא, parsha da, let me go over this פרשה, parsha, ואתנייה, v'asnayyah,
and let me repeat it. So ולשנותה ulishnosah comes from the word
שני. sheni. need to do it a second time, not from the
word like לשנן leshanen which means like משנה Mishna? and gets to
sort of the idea of a rabbinic teaching. Let's just read one
more line and then I'll say something about this. איתמר נמי אמר
רבי חלבו אמר עולא ביראה: Itmar nami amar Rabbi Chelbo amar Ulla
Bira: חייב אדם לקרות את המגילה בלילה ולשנותה ביום. hayav adam likros
es ha-migilla ba-laila u-leshonosa ba-yom. You have to read it at night
and repeat it in the day based on a different פסוק, pasuk,
a פסוק pasuk more about the the miracle than about the crying
out, שנאמר: shene'emar: למען יזמרך כבוד ולא ידום, lema'an yezamercha chavod ve-lo
yidom, not be silent. Again, interesting the word דום dom appears in
both of those. ולא ידום ve-lo yidom ה׳ אלהי לעולם אודך. Hashem
Elokai le'olam odeka. So the idea of all the time, לילה ויום,
laila va-yom, is a way of framing like it's a constant sense
of throughout the day, framing the day of of praising God for
the miracle. So by the way, that's interesting in the two aspects
it expresses of this like פרסומי ניסא, pirsumei nisa, first the צרה
tzara is part of that story and then it's the obviously the
praise and the miracle. But I want to say two things about
about this. First of all, the idea that there was a הוה
אמינא hava amina that you learn the משניות Mishnayos in the day
rather than reading it in the day; it gets back to a
theme I've been mentioning, which is about the innovation of the מגילה
Megillah but through חז״ל. Chazal. חז״ל Chazal were the ones that decided
that it was one of the ספרי תנ״ך. Sifrei Tanakh. חז״ל Chazal
are the ones that are seen in the first דף daf of
מגילה on אנשי כנסת הגדולה Anshei Knesset HaGedolah were the one that
were מתקן metakein the מקרא מגילה, mikra Megillah not that it we're
doing it because it's in the מגילה but because אנשי כנסת הגדולה
Anshei Knesset HaGedolah were מתקן metakein it. We're learning all the הלכות
in a classic rabbinic way through a דרשנות darshaning of the פסוקים.
psukim, So I think it's interesting like the הוה אמינא hava amina
of, oh, instead of reading the מגילה we'll learn it before. If
the if it falls out on שבת, instead of reading it you
have a דרשה drasha of it. So here we thought, oh, we
read it last night, so in the day, instead of reading it
we'll learn the משניות. Mishnayos. So this whole issue of sort of
of the rabbinic mode, and let's face it, the מגילה's coming at
a time when you're sort of transitioning, right, it's right at the
בית שני Bayis Sheni period when you're transitioning from the from the
period of נבואה nevuah to the period of
rabbinic, it's a little early in the rabbinic period, but it's עזרא
הסופר, Ezra HaSofer, right, so it's right at that sort of juxtaposition
of the נבואה nevuah and the type of תלמוד תורה, talmud Torah,
תורה שבעל פה. Torah she-ba'al peh. So again, it's interesting here, the
thought that that could replace the מקרא מגילה is the learning of
the משניות. Mishnayos. The other thing though that's very important to mention
is the phrasing here makes it sound like the reading of night
is more important. You have to read it at night and repeat
it during
the day. However, all of the משניות Mishnayos that we're going to
read coming up talk about the מצוה mitzvah of מגילה being a
מצוה mitzvah of the day. It says when does the מצוה mitzvah
of מגילה start? On עלות השחר alos ha-shachar or from הנץ החמה,
haneitz ha-chammah, etc. מצוה Mitzvah of מגילה is a day מצוה. mitzvah.
And basically the way some of the אחרונים Achronim frame this is
that reading the מגילה in the day is a מצוה מדברי סופרים
mitzvah mi-divrei sofrim because it's based on פסוקים, psukim. whereas reading the
מגילה at night is a מצוה דרבנן. mitzvah de-rabbanan. Okay, that's a
pure rabbinic, not based on the פסוקים. But the sort of primary
פסוק pasuk based, although פסוק pasuk through the interpretation of חז״ל Chazal
as we've been saying, but primary פסוק pasuk based מצוה mitzvah is
in the day and night is more halakhically secondary and was added
later, although the phrasing here sounds the opposite. תוספות tries to reread
the phrasing to get the day to be more important and that's
clear from all the evidence. It's very important because everybody thinks the
night is more important because it's better, it's an easier time to
bring the whole family and that's when the shuls do their whole
big to-do is at night. But halakhically speaking, if you had to
choose between going to a מגילה reading at night or a מגילה
reading in the day, you go to מגילה reading in the day.
And a lot of people aren't מקפיד makpid enough to go the
next day; they went the previous night. But the next day is
the primary מצוה mitzvah of מגילה, the phrasing of this notwithstanding. Okay,
let's turn the page. אלא שכבר מקדימין ליום הכניסה. Ella she-kevar makdimin
l'yom ha-knisa. אמר רבי חנינה, Amar Rabbi Chanina, so the villages start
Monday and Thursday. חכמים הקילו על הכפרים להיות מקדימין ליום הכניסה. Chachamim
he-kilu al ha-kefarim lihyos makdimin l'yom ha-knisa. The sages were easy for
the villages to let them do the reading on the market days
כדי שיספקו מים ומזון לאחיהם שבכרכים, kedei she-yispeku mayim u-mazon la-acheihem she-ba-krakhim,
in order that they should provide water and food to their brethren
in the large cities. Okay, now, first of all, I just want
to say one thing, number one about Monday and Thursday. The first
רש״י, Rashi, I wasn't here when you did the first דף, daf,
the first רש״י Rashi says it's because it's the day where the
בתי דינים batei dinim are קבועים kevuim and therefore everybody's coming into
the main town in order to go to a בית דין. Beis
Din. Now, how many people need to go to a בית דין?
Beis Din? So רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel said it's not because the
בתי דינים batei dinim are there, he says that's the idea of
the phrasing of רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel on דף ב׳ עמוד א׳
daf beiz amud aleph was let me just read it here.
It says just like
this: מפני שנכנסים בני הכפרים לכרכים כדי שיתפללו בציבור ויקראו בספר תורה.
mipnei she-nichnasin bnei ha-kefarim la-krakhim kedei she-yitpalelu be-tzibbur ve-yikre'u be-Sefer Torah. So
it's quite interesting. He says because it was a day that you
read the ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, people wanted to at least come
to shul. You know, you don't come to shul on a daily
basis. But now the reason is in order to provide, you know,
bread and food for their brethren in the larger cities, makes it
sound like we're going to try to get it for you, this
is for you to come early, not to read the מגילה on
a day we're
reading. You guys, like it's you know, like the catering, like the
people that work in the kitchen, you have your meal beforehand and
then you'll and then you'll serve everybody else. You guys take care
of your reading of the מגילה beforehand so on פורים itself you'll
be available to have your stores open for the people of the
big cities, which really puts them in a very second-class type of
a status. The גמרא is going to reframe this. So let's just
read one line and flip the page. למימרא Lemaymra says the גמרא,
this suggests that תקנתא דכרכים הוי, tikunta dekrachim havi, we're doing all
of this to make things better for the big cities. והתנן, Vehatnan,
didn't we teach in a משנה? Notice by the way here, כרך
is used to mean a city of the 14th, not a walled
city of the 15th. So that's a little confusing, gets back to
the point we made before about the עשרה בטלנים. Does כרך mean
walled cities or does it mean a large unwalled city? Anyway, that
we're doing all this for the large cities. והתנן חל להיות בשני
כפרים ועיירות גדולות קורין בו ביום. Vehatnan chal lihyot besheni kefarim veayarot
gedolot korin bo bayom. If it's on a Monday, everybody reads on
the same day. If you're going to make these people read early
to be available, then they should always read early. Even when it
falls out on a Monday. ואי איתא, Ve-im itah, if you're doing
this to make it easier for the big city, ליקדמו ליום הכניסה,
likdumu leyom hakenisa, even when it's on a Monday, make these guys
read on a Thursday. No, הא לא עשר, ha lo asar, then
you'll be back to the tenth of אדר. Adar. ועשרה לא תקינו
רבנן, Ve-asar lo takinu rabanan, and you know, when we learned only
X number of days, you can't go back to the tenth. Okay,
let's try again. תא שמע חל להיות בחמישי כפרים ועיירות גדולות קורין
בו ביום. Tashma chal lihyot behamishi kefarim veayarot gedolot korin bo bayom.
They read, everybody reads on Thursday. ואי
איתא, Ve-im itah, and
if they're trying to דווקא davka make these guys go early, ליקדמו
ליום הכניסה, likdumu leyom hakenisa, let them read instead of on Thursday
on a Monday. דחד עשר הוא, Dehad asar hu, it's the 11th
of
אדר. Adar. מיום הכניסה ליום הכניסה לא דחנינן. Miyom hakenisa leyom hakenisa
lo dachnina. Nah, it's you know, we have to have, we keep
it on a market day. We're not going to push it off
to a different one, which doesn't really answer the question. Okay, תא
שמע אמר רבי יהודה אימתי, Tashma amar Rabbi Yehuda ematai, I'm getting
to the dot dot. אימתי במקום שנכנסים בשני ובחמישי. Ematai bimkom shenichnasim
besheni uvehamishi. When is it that we go early? In places where
the villages come in on a Monday and a Thursday. אבל מקום
שאין נכנסים בשני ובחמישי אין קורין אלא בזמנה. Aval makom she-ein nichnasim
besheni uvehamishi ein korin ela bizmana. If the villages don't usually come
in on a Monday and
Thursday, then you don't have them read early. ואי סלקא דעתך תקנתא
דכרכים היא, Ve-itah salka daitach tikunta dekrachim hi, but if the whole
thing is for the betterment of the large cities, what do I
care if they don't normally come in? Let them come in, let
them read it, so they'll be available to take care of the
large cities. משום דאין נכנסים בשני ובחמישי מפסידו לכרכים? Mishum de-ein nichnasim
besheni uvehamishi mifsedu lekrachim? Like you know, what is it like they
said, you know, because you had a bad day why should I
suffer? Right? So, you know that line from Fiddler on the Roof?
You know, just because you don't come in, so what? Come in
so you'll be available for the big cities, if that's really what's
going on here. So the גמרא says: Okay, let's reverse it. לא
תימא כדי שיספקו מים ומזון, Lo tema k’dei sheyispaku mayim umazon, it's
not we make it, we do it so that they'll provide for
the larger cities. We don't do it for the sake of the
larger cities. אלא אימא, Ela eima, read it the opposite way.
מפני שמספקין מים ומזון לאחיהם שבכרכים. Mifne shemesapkim mayim umazon leachiam shebekrachim.
Because they generally, and this is the way רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel
reads it, since in general you come in on the market days
and you're there to provide, you know, you do all these things
that are the for the betterment of the larger cities, therefore we're
going to be nice to you and make it easy for you.
So we're going to this is to make it easier for the
villages, it's not to make it more convenient for the large cities.
And רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel says anyway, what's happening is they're not
providing food on פורים. They're coming in on the market days so
that everybody can buy their provisions for פורים. Because the way רבינו
חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel says it is he said if you didn't do
this what would happen? They would say I'm not coming in on
Thursday, I have to come in anyway tomorrow because tomorrow is פורים.
And therefore the markets won't be open on Thursday. So if you
want to have the markets open on the Monday and Thursday, you
make it convenient for them to read on that day as well.
But ultimately because of the general service that they provide, that's why
we're doing this for their sake, not for the sake of the
larger cities.